Professional Summary

- 10+ years of IT industry experience encompassing a wide range of skill set, roles and industry verticals.
- Extensive work experience in all phases of Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) including Requirement Analysis, Design, Coding, Testing and Implementation in Agile (Scrum), TDD Environment.
- Cloud experience with AWS using Lambda, Step functions, S3 buckets, IAM and Secret Manager.

Technical Skills

Front End Technologies	HTML, JavaScript, React, jQuery, CSS, Bootstrap, JSP, AngularJS, NodeJS
Back End Technologies	Java 17, Spring boot 3, Apache Camel, Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Artifactory, Apigee, Grafana,
	Pentaho, Kafka, Spring AOP, Scala, Spring MVC, JSF, Log4j, Ant, WEB-SERVICES (REST, SOAP, WSDL,
	Axis2, CXF, JAX RS)
IT Security tools	Symantec VIP
IT Security	Spring Security, JWT, OAuth
Cloud Technologies	AWS, S3, Fargate, Lambda, Step functions, IAM, Secret Manager, SQS
CI CD and Dev Ops	Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins
Databases	Oracle 8i/9i/10g/11g, SQL Server, DB2, SQL Lite, MySQL, JDBC.
Information	JSON, XML, XSD, WSDL
Application Servers	Tomcat, JBoss, ISS, WebSphere, WebLogic Server, OC4J Application Server
Other	Visio, Teams, Micro
Versioning	SVN, GitHub
Documentation	UML
Methodology	Agile, SCRUM
O.S.	Linux, Windows

Education

Universidad Tecnológica de Jalisco Guadalajara, Jalisco, México 2012

Bachelors in Computer Systems engineer

Languages

Spanish Native English Fluent

Certifications

Oracle Certified Professional, Java SE 6 Programmer Certification 2015

Work Experience

Environment: Java 17, AWS, Spring Boot,, Tomcat, Hibernate 3.5, JPA2, Maven, XML, Spring Security, Kafka, RabbitMQ, IntelijIDEA, JSON, GIT, RestFul Api, Scala, PostMan, Junit, Mockito, Agile, Scrum.

MAR 2022 - ACTUAL

Company: Hexaware, Mexico

Role: Java Full Stack

Responsibilities:

- Microservice development and consumption using Spring boot 3 framework.
- Hybris application maintenance.
- · Grafana report generation.
- CI/CD using Jenkins pipelines.
- Unit test development.
- · Code reviews.
- Kafka message broker topic consumptions.
- AWS S3 consumption.
- EC2 instance management.
- Apache Camel route implementation for step functions redrive system
- AWS Lambdas creation wrapped in step functions.
- SQS creation and consumption for data push/pull in several microservice.

• Scala legacy code maintenance and migration.

Environment: Java 11-17, Spring Boot, Apache Free Maker, DB2, Unix, JavaScript, React, Tomcat, Hibernate 3.5, JPA2, Maven, XML, Spring Security, IntelijIDEA, AWS, Lambda, S3, JSON, GIT, RestFul Api, PostMan, Junit, Mockito, Selenium, Cucumber, Agile, Scrum.

SEP 2019 - MAR 2022

Company: Digital on us, Mexico

Role: Java Full Stack

Responsibilities:

- Email templates creation using Apache Freemarker, JavaScript and CSS.
- · Config creation using Pegasus Mail framework.
- Kibana report generation.
- CI/CD using Jenkins pipelines.
- Develop web application using company internal tool from scratch to Revolve staff.
- API creation and consumption using Spring Boot.
- Health portal maintenance and improvements using react.
- RDMS MySQL database integration, normalization and interaction.
- Manual / Automated testing using selenium.
- AWS S3 content consumption.
- EC2 instance usage.
- Lambda with step functions creation, modification and consumption.
- Code reviews

Environment: Java 8-11, Spring Boot, MySQL, SQL Server, JavaScript, React, Tomcat, Hibernate 3.5, JPA2, Maven, XML, Spring Security, IntelijIDEA, JSON, GIT, RestFul Api, AWS, Lambda, S3, Kafka, RabbitMq, PostMan, Junit, Mockito, Agile, Scrum, JMeter.

Company: Cognizant, Mexico JAN 2019 – SEP 2019

Role: Java Developer

Responsibilities:

- Microservices development using Spring Boot, Hibernate, Swagger and DB2 for an important food retailer company.
- Jmeter scripts test load development for several APIs.
- Legacy web app applications (JSP, JavaScript vainilla).
- TDD enhancement in order to cover 80% of code
- PR review from junior peers as well mentoring and guidance.

Environment: Java 8, Spring Boot, MySQL, SQL Server, JavaScript, AngularJS, React, Redux, Tomcat, Hibernate 3.5, JPA2, Maven, XML, Spring Security, IntelijIDEA, JSON, GIT, RestFul Api,, PostMan, Junit, Mockito, Agile, Scrum.

DEC 2016 - JAN 2019

Company: Softek, Mexico Role: Java Full Stack

Responsibilities:

- ERP Spring Boot microservices development working along with technologies as Apache Camel for routing, Docker and Eureka framework. Cassandra NoSql database iteration and management. Angular JS modules development and testing.
- Full Stack Development using React and Spring boot microservices for banking. Web application build for MSR member who take care all inbound calls from customers. Spring Boot microservices creation and consumption.
- Validate ACH File integrity depending on the channel through Java 8. Migration effort through WAS to WildFly environment. Front end development using React Redux framework. HPSB middleware A to A application Java 8 module development.
- Data Governance Portal Web application development through React, Redux
- Grommet, SASS. MDM Portal Sales Territory module backend development using Java 7 and Oracle 12c PLSQL development.
- TDD using Junit and Mockito to write test cases. Agile/Scrum methodology during all the projects.
- Code reviews

Environment: Java 7, Spring MVC, JavaScript, React, Redux, Tomcat, Maven, XML, IntelijIDEA, JSON, SVN, RestFul Api, Junit, Mockito.

MAY 2016 - DEC 2016

Company: IBM, Mexico Role: Java Developer

Description: I worked in IBM in subversion control tool call Rational Team Concert. I was in charge to develop new feature at backend/frontend side and maintain the application as well. Other hand we built several Eclipse plugins for different companies like BOSCH or CitiBanamex for software teams.

Responsibilities:

- Software development to Rational Team Concert (IBM subversion control software) in order to improve the functionality to the size customer requirements.
- Lifecycle Management (CLM, IBM software management software). Front End Development using React Reddux frameworks for ERP application that consume RestFul web services.
- Unit test development.
- Code Review.
- · India team daily handoff.

Environment: Java 7, Spring MVC, JavaScript, JQuery, Tomcat, Maven, XML, Eclipse, XML, SVN, SOAP, Informix.

JAN 2015 - MAY 2016

Company: Group Z, Mexico Role: Java Developer

Responsibilities:

- System migration partially to JSF framework/Spring MVC also mobile application development in Android Studio to have the street sales control of gas. Responsive web development using JQuery and Bootstrap.
- UI/UX meeting with designers.
- End User requirements meeting.
- · Code reviews.
- Unit test/Funcional Test.

Environment: Java FX, XML, Eclipse, XML, SVN, SQL Server, OpenGL, SOAP, ASP, C#.

SEP 2012 - DEC 2014

Company: Medisist, Mexico Role: Java Developer

Responsibilities:

- Software development for biomedical devices (Electrocardiogram, Glucose Meters, Presion Meters) for control and user interaction. Using Java 1.6, Spring MVC and Restful.
- Software development for electronically billing using a web portal for minors' clients and custom software (Virtual Bridge project) for specific clients. Development with.NET framework (C#, Windows Form, ASP, SOAP Web Services).
- End User requirements meetings.
- Code reviews.
- Unit test/Funcional Test.